Meeting will be called to order.
Mr. Bloom, can we do a roll call,
please?
>> Remember roll call.
Chad Halverson.
>> Present.
>> Rob Graham.
>> Katie Ames.
>> Present.
>> Ryan Whitehead.
>> And Ken Duggas.
>> Present.
>> Chair, we have a quorum.
>> Thank you.
The first item on the agenda is
disclosures.
Do we have any disclosures?
Hearing none, we'll move on to the
minutes. Has everybody had an
opportunity to review the minutes from
September 4th, 2025 and February 5th,
2026?
Okay.
Any comment or
uh clarifications on the minutes?
Hearing none, we'll vote to approve the
minutes.
>> I'll make a motion.
>> Thank you. Do you have a second?
>> I'll second.
>> Okay.
All those in favor of approval of the
minutes, say aye.
>> Aye.
>> Those opposed,
>> Motion carries.
Okay. The next item is the citywide
blight designation
to resend and consider.
Mr. Bloom.
>> Um chair, members of the of the board.
Um I got the right agenda up now. I had
the wrong one up on accident. Apologies
for that. Um so, what this is is this
item is
pretty straightforward. Essentially,
it's revisiting the document that we
considered at our last meeting, which
was the citywide blight study.
That one was highly predicated on the
completion of our county pockets
annexation action, which uh did seem to
take a different path
immediately after our meeting. Um it
kind of got derailed, for lack of a
better term, and it got postponed until
uh the 6th of actually the 9th of
November.
Um so, what this is is this essentially
is to move forward with
um the blight study as the city limits
exist today. So, what that will
effectively do is it will remove
10 um of the county pockets from the
blight designation.
Uh that means for those properties that
within the areas that are unincorporated
county pockets right now, um in the
event that they get annexed, they would
have to
on their own extend that blight
designation.
Um I would like to note that since the
last consideration, the sister city
limits here, um we have closed a
significant um amount of properties that
were county islands at that time. Um
notable ones include section 20, um that
area uh behind the Walmart Frontier
Mall, um as well as a lot of the
properties out in Sunnyside addition, um
and such. Really, the there are only a
couple of holes um that do exist still
in this area.
Uh
one of them is located out on East
College Drive. You can see it here. This
is where the Pepsi bottling facility is.
There's an old barn there. We haven't
had any uh true inquiries for uh blight
designation or urban renewal in that
area.
The most significant um parcel size
would be uh this larger one on Walter
Schiedt, south of Fox Farm. It's the
Wyffels Farms area. Um that one doesn't
appear to have any interest in utilizing
tax increment financing for development,
um as well as uh several small
residential uh properties and a couple
of just small isolated properties that
are that are out there.
Um so that's effectively what this um
this does and I can
I would also like to just highlight what
we've
done in the report.
Um really we've we haven't made too many
changes. We have just a a couple of
items noting what's changed. We enhanced
the map a little bit by identifying US
85 on the map. That was an oversight
earlier so it gives people a better
ability to put it all in the context. Um
we did add a new paragraph which is on
page four which basically
reflects the um
uh the acknowledgement that we're we're
not including the county islands.
Um and then we
um made a couple of grammatical errors
that I had noticed were outstanding um
regarding uh one map for the Yellowstone
uh blight designation examples and the
South Holiday um blight designations.
They really weren't uh too significant
but they were worthy of correction.
Um I will and we also added an appendix
uh C
which shows what we're calling the
excluded enclaves.
And what we did there is we essentially
um used the uh surveyed maps that were
put together for the annexation. And we
um added those as an appendix. They can
made the total documents about 112 pages
um
now.
So I'll show you where that new area is.
It is
where did I put it? It's right here.
It's this one paragraph here at the end.
The blight designation encompasses the
entirety of the city limits as existed
upon adoption which would be um when the
governing body does adopt this, excluded
um
unincorporated county enclaves are
identified in appendix C.
If we go all the way down to appendix C
at the very end of this monster
document.
I'm very happy that the
ADA requirements were postponed so I
didn't have to do alt captions for every
single one of these images, but in the
future we probably will.
Everything in the rest of the document
has been acknowledged.
We have our appendix C excluded
enclaves.
Uh, this is added. This just shows the
areas that have been excluded.
Um, and then it has there the maps that
were provided um as part of that action.
Uh, staff um does recognize that this uh
that this um
document is actually kind of in limbo
between the urban renewal authority and
the governing body right now because we
were waiting.
Um, with that wait we believe the
appropriate action would be to
um number one rescind
uh the previous recommendation
that you all had made at your February
5th, 2026 meeting.
Um, and then to adopt or to recommend
approval of the
um
of the revised one. So, we have two
motions here. I'm going to note that
that should say 2026 not 2025.
Um, but this is these are the two
motions that we would recommend if you
would like to move forward with that
adoption.
I'm open for any questions that you may
have. Oh, and I should note sorry before
I I jump around real quick. Um, I should
note since the since the beginning of
the year we have had a lot of different
property owners and developers that are
looking at building in the community
that have
asked about how they can utilize tax
increment financing and they all
recognize that the blight study is the
first step and it allows them to open up
the toolbox to see if they can qualify
for tax increment financing. Um so,
several folks have been patiently
waiting for this to be approved so they
can begin to investigate their projects.
Um some of those properties are located
uh on the east part of town near college
uh drive out that location kind of near
uh Jimmy John's is is one that's at one
that frequently pops up. Um there's
other um ones that are located in the
areas behind Frontier Mall, um some
other areas off of Del Range Boulevard.
So, there are a lot of uh developers who
have ideas and ambitions and even on the
south side as well and they have ideas
and ambitions and they've been patiently
waiting and we thought it was
appropriate to remove that waiting game
from them and let them be able to start
to fully investigate the possibilities
of utilizing TIF.
So, I will field any questions that you
all may have.
>> Chair Furry.
Chair Furry, you had a just quick
question. What are the steps, I guess
maybe I missed it when
you know, the if the city does annex
these county pockets, what would be the
steps to are there additional steps at
that point at that action point when
they become annexed?
>> Yes, great question uh board member
Whitehead. They will um what will happen
is
they will have to request that this
document be amended. Um likely they will
have to either seek a private consultant
um unless staff has additional time to
do it to um evaluate how their specific
pocket um does
fall into the surrounding conditions of
blight um to add it to the to the
to this document as an addendum.
Uh we did primarily envision this to
occur when properties annex
um, because the interpretation um,
through our legal department, even after
I look at it as well, um, is we can't
automatically extend our area of
operation, um, concurrently with the
city limits, um, by action of
annexation. We would have to revisit it
independently, but that visitation could
be concurrent with the annexation
ordinance. And that's how we would treat
it.
>> Thank you. That answers my question.
>> Any other questions or comments before
we move to motions?
Okay.
Hearing none, do I have a motion?
>> Chair, through you, I move to rescind
the recommendation made on February 5th,
2026,
recommending approval of an updated
blight study to apply to the entirety of
the city limits.
>> I'll second.
>> It's been seconded. Any further
discussion on the motions?
My procedure's getting rusty, guys.
Hearing none, we will vote on the
motion. All those in favor, say aye.
>> Aye.
>> Motion passes.
If any we There's a second motion,
right? Okay.
>> And chair, if I may elaborate a little
bit on the second motion why it's a lot
longer than before. If we recall, um, at
the last meeting in February, there was
some discussion on making sure we were
very clear in tying it to the required
findings under state statute for
designation of blight.
Uh,
in the report, you'll notice that there
are 10 different blight criterion that
are mentioned.
Uh, eight of those There's There's 10 in
state statute. Eight of those are
referenced in the report throughout
various areas of town. And these are the
eight.
So, we would,
um,
like whoever is going to make the motion
to at least highlight all of those items
that are on there.
>> Who wants to read a paragraph?
I think I can move, right? I can make my
own motions. Yeah,
we have we no more miss meetings.
>> Okay.
>> I will move to recommend the governing
body approve the blight study expansion
noting the blight study highlights the
following conditions of blight are
located within the city constituting a
blighted area substantially impairing
sound municipal growth, retarding house
housing development and constituting an
economic or social liability.
One, deteriorated or deteriorating
structures. Two, predominance of
defective or inadequate street layout.
Three, faulty lot layout in relation to
size, accessibility, or usefulness.
Four, unsanitary or unsafe conditions.
Five, deterioration of site or other
improvements. Six, diversity of
ownership, tax, or other special
assessments. Seven, the existence of
conditions which endanger life or
property by fire and other causes. And
eight, poor platting.
>> Second.
>> Thank you.
Any further discussion on the motion?
All those in favor,
>> Say aye.
>> Aye.
Motion carries.
>> All right, thank you very much, uh chair
and board.
>> I like the poor platting part.
>> Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> That's Don't get me started.
>> It happens.
>> It doesn't objective.
>> [laughter]
>> Well, it's it's objective and it's a
headache in some a lot of areas, so.
>> Yes.
Okay. Um the next item on the agenda is
the annual report.
Mr. Bloom.
>> Chair members of the
um this is intended to uh
be enough to meet the statutory and the
municipal code requirements regarding
our annual report. Um what's really
interesting with the way our reports are
put together for the URA is they do not
follow a federal fiscal year or the
state fiscal year. They follow the
calendar year. So this report is as of
December 31st, 2025.
Um so what we've seen here um is
additional revenue um that has and I
should note on this when we're looking
at fiscal year 2026,
that is actually highlighting the time
period between July 1 of 2025 and
December 31st of 2025. So that's why you
see fiscal year 2026
on that um that chart.
I I would also like to note that uh
since
uh the end of calendar year 2025, we did
receive our first significant tax
increment financing payments
um for the Hitching Post uh urban
renewal plan and project area. So that
is not reflected here, but it will be
reflected on the next
uh annual report because that was
revenue that was received during
calendar year 2026.
>> How much was it?
>> I knew you would ask and I had to wanted
to um pull that up. I believe it was
right around 67,000,
somewhere in there.
Um
I'd have to double double check again. I
had I did not have time to look, but it
was
it was um short of expectations.
Um but it's not uh so short that it
would
uh preclude itself from actually gaining
the increment over the whole life of the
tax increment financing development
agreement
um it's just not
accruing as expected due to a slower
than expected development um in that
area.
>> Chair, through you, uh Charles, might
that be the note that you made at the
bottom of page four of the annual
report?
>> Chair, that is correct. Um I
>> amount is included in my
>> Back with the amount in there?
>> $60,951,
does that sound right?
>> Chair, that is correct, yes.
I forgot to put that note in there. It's
been a blur lately.
So, that is that there's a note in there
that that's not reflected. That will be
reflected in the 2026 report.
But, as you can see, um we did have some
significant um increases uh over uh 2025
um
that had occurred. The expenses you see
in fiscal year 2025
um that would be the first half of 2025
um of $16,797.50
um that was the uh
payment to the third-party reviewer for
the MHP
uh
uh third-party review of their um
of their pro forma identifying that they
had a
a gap, relatively large gap, if you all
recall that meeting. Um that that's what
that one is. Um that one we're pretty
darn close to finalizing the development
um agreement. We have a draft
development agreement that's been put
together.
Um I need to reach back out to them
again
um to relay conversations I've had with
our city attorney on how um we will move
forward with identifying um authorized
activities uh associated with that
project.
>> [snorts]
>> But, as you can see, um with the
project, we have some pretty um hefty
balances in our account. I should note
that with the Hitching Post, it does
show $96,891.
Um the revenue that we've received for
that urban renewal plan and project
area, that's for a large area, includes
lands commonly known as the back 40. It
includes the Hampton Inn that's under
construction. It includes the EverHome
Suites, the I Center Event Center, and
all of that. Right now, the only pledge
that the urban with the city has through
the urban renewal authority um for
repayment of any tax increment is only
for
um properties that formerly were the
hitching post property proper. So,
that's about five lots. The only one
that's developed is the EverHome Suites.
So, whenever we have a tax revenue
payment for that specific
tax parcel,
um that is what is eligible to be
reimbursed back to developer.
So, any gains we see from like the
Hampton Inn, uh that goes into the
fiduciary fund where once that gathers
um enough funding, we as the board can
consider it. We can make recommendations
to the governing body as to how uh that
money should be spent to carry out the
urban renewal plan.
So, that is going to be exciting because
we will be expecting to see probably
about $60,000 a year that will be at
least that would be generated from that
Hampton Inn hotel project that would be
uh funds that could be utilized for
urban renewal activities.
And yes, chair, through you. Charles, um
Banner Capital was the financier for for
the for the that property, those
properties. I don't know how many they
were involved with.
Are
maybe this is an inappropriate question,
but are they going to come out?
>> Chair uh through you to Commissioner
Andrus and I'm I'm
assuming are they going to be able to be
developed? Is that
what we're looking the question is?
>> I'm I'm just concerned if
any loss will
be incurred by them.
>> Chair members of the board, I'm in
looking at the numbers and ultimately
looking at what development is going to
look at in that area. I do not
anticipate that in the long term that
Banner Capital will have a a loss. I'm
even looking at the revenues we're
receiving today based on the hotel and
assuming that anything develops on the
other properties which I can't imagine
nothing ever occurring out there. It is
going to more than
settle the tax increment pledge that was
made.
Um the
pledge and the calculations initially
that was very conservative very
conservative just because we didn't want
to over promise. So I'm not anticipating
it is behind right now, but any all the
costs that interest
that amount those are able to be covered
under the TIFF agreement up to the
maximum.
>> Thank you. I think that's important.
>> Mr. Bloom, sorry I have a question too.
So with the funds how are they held? Are
they held in like savings account? Does
the city hold it? Do you invest those
funds or do they just sit in the savings
account? Like what does that look like?
>> Chair members of the board, at least
we're not holding it in like a little
suitcase or something tucked under a
chair.
No, actually we
as you know as you see on this we have
interest
that is paid. We don't have interest for
fiscal year 2023 and notably because it
was a new process we're receiving our
first increments.
What we do is we take the money and then
we have the
it's an investment fund that's
authorized by the state of Wyoming and
that investment fund
gains presently about 3.8% interest. So
we're gaining interest on that money and
we don't have any penalties for pulling
it out. We can put money in, we can pull
money out. Um a lot of our accounts
where we are just holding other funds
like this one of the DDAs um
uh mill levy, those ones are put into
what's called as the W G um
I F, it's the Wyoming
government investment fund
and we can
put it in and pull it out really quick.
Uh it used to be about 5% interest. It
just kind of changes, you know, with the
the financial tide um but it's still
um a pretty decent return right now.
>> Yeah, okay. I was just curious.
>> So but it's held there. We work with our
our treasurer's office to to track it
and make sure.
So that's uh the financial report. The
next steps for this would be to um we'll
send it to the governing body for their
acceptance. They'll just accept it um
and then we'll have it um on file at the
clerk's office for public inspection.
Um the only motion I would seek on this
would be just a
motion to acknowledge receipt. I don't
have a cheater slide for you all
um but that's the only motion we'd be
looking for.
>> Chair, through you I move to acknowledge
receipt of the annual report.
>> Second.
>> Okay.
All those in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Okay. The next item, sorry, were you
you're done with the annual report?
Okay.
>> That's correct.
>> The next item on our agenda is other
business.
Do you have any other business?
>> Yes, Chair, members of the board. We do
have a reappointments
um that are occurring for all of our
different boards every few years. And
presently
we have one member
whose term will be expiring on the
urban renewal authority.
I thought I could just pull that up and
it would have said in the email, but
it's going to make me look.
So, if you know your term is expiring,
does anyone know if their term is
expiring?
I'm going to look it up real quick. And
you'd like to be reappointed to the
board?
>> No idea.
>> Okay.
>> It's me.
>> Oh.
I'm out of here. You guys are on your
own.
>> Yes, uh chair, it is it is you. You are
the one who's expiring on in
June of 2026. Um I have to update the
website.
Um I do believe that uh
board member Whitehead and Graham have
both been reappointed already.
So, if you have a desire to um stay on,
just send us an email. If you
um don't, send us an email as well if
you don't want to talk about it here. We
understand. We can let everyone just
hang out here.
>> I have to stay.
>> Okay.
>> My favorite board.
>> [laughter]
>> We just saying something.
A lot of boards.
>> All right. The only other item for or
two other items I have for other
business is uh we are going through our
annual budget.
Um
you'll see a lot of work sessions that
are in front of the governing body. They
started yesterday at noon and they'll be
going through Friday the 15th. All the
departments will be making their
requests. Uh we have a general fund
budget that has increased to $80 million
from $74 million last year.
The mayor has indicated that when he
first came on with his first term, the
city's general fund budget was $55
million. So, we've had a significant
increase.
Um
the general fund, I think most of you
all know, but I'll just echo it, that
pays for everything that's not a
franchise fee.
Uh so, you take out Board of Public
Utilities, you take out anything that's
operating on a revenue basis.
Um
take out solid waste, those items is
basically everything that's public
serving. It's building, it's planning,
it's the city attorney's office, the
mayor's office, the finance department,
those those different groups.
Um it's also items that aren't grant
funded.
Um a lot of that additional 80 or the
additional funding we've seen is through
one-time fees that we're getting quite
consistently for data center
developments.
Um those mostly have not been ever
allocated as
um
as
expected ongoing expenses. They usually
go to our a reserve account. Um but when
we do have these large electricity users
that are in the community, those folks
are paying sales tax.
Um and also a franchise fee on the use
of electricity.
Um for example, I I do know that some of
our heavy power users, you know, they
can have um tax payments of up to
$180,000
per month um just based on the electric
electricity um taxes and franchise fees.
So, a small Bitcoin operation, these
large of operation, you know, that can
translate into almost a you know, just
over a million dollars per year. Uh
similarly, we're working on pinning down
the numbers for what data centers like,
you know, Microsoft and those things are
are generating per hole. But those um
dollar amounts are really helping us
continue to
um enhance our services and hopefully
continue to improve the quality of life
of the city of Cheyenne. So, um we'll
see how that continues to move forward
through the um through the process.
Any questions on that?
Here through you.
>> Uh you mentioned data centers.
>> Mhm.
>> How how does how how does that dynamic
work regarding
uh TIF?
>> Great question.
And chair members of the board, to board
member Dugas,
I've had uh
several inquiries from data centers
specifically
um not the mainstream ones that we've
seen like Microsoft and and Meta and a
couple of other larger ones where
they've actually inquired about
utilizing tax increment financing to
offset some of their costs. It's
probably the fair way to put it. Um
they've wanted to relocate utility
lines, transmission lines, install
transmission lines using tax increment
financing.
Um the biggest thing we're looking at is
when we approve
a tax increment financing uh development
agreement, we're looking to make sure
that that
entity is proving that there is a
financial gap
in their pro forma that prevents them
from doing business.
That is the one thing that I do not
believe that they're able to
demonstrate and
the conversation ends pretty quickly. Um
I won't blame anyone for asking. Um but
if it's a data center, which those earn
generally a lot of revenue,
we are not going to be
looking to um
to encourage or entertain tax increment
financing unless they can truly
demonstrate a gap. And again, this would
be across their entire portfolio. So,
these are large companies with national
or international footprint. So, it would
be, I think, very challenging to
identify a gap.
>> Although, and I agree with that, and you
know, the purpose of of TIF financing,
but if they were asking for and I guess
I just don't know the math on it. Like
if the what their property taxes would
be every year. Like if we did a plan and
project and say
they wanted 3 million for utilities, but
they're paying a million in property
taxes every year, and it's a $30 million
deal, that might make sense to then get
some funding into the pot to then be
able to help other projects, right? I
mean, that would be how it would work
cuz we can use those funds for other It
doesn't have to be just in that
designated area, yeah.
>> Chair, three of you, that is correct. Um
I've looked at
I've compared the Walmart to a Microsoft
data center hall. They're almost the
exact same square footage. Their
assessment values differ substantially
um because you're assessing the property
based on the fixtures and a lot of the
equipment that's in there. That's
uh a fixture that is
assessed.
Um rule of thumb that I've noticed is
that
for every one square foot of
Walmart square footage, you'll see two
and a half times the assessment for a a
data center.
Um which that would create a healthy
increment.
Uh there is nothing prohibiting us from
creating a plan and project at a
municipal level which can capture the
tax revenue from an individual parcel
and then designate that revenue to
basically mitigate, remediate, halt, or
stop the spread of slumber blight in an
area nearby. So, that is definitely
something we could do. Um however, that
would have to you'd have to go through
the plan and project process. It'd have
to be ultimately approved by the
governing body and there would have to
be a lot of
discussion and probably caution taken to
make sure that we are
doing it within the political will uh
statewide.
Um we wouldn't want that to
be looked at as us just
grabbing all of the new revenue from the
data centers and using it for our
purposes.
So there'd have to be um some
discussions on how to walk that walk
that line.
Um it's my understanding that when
the city center city's not the city
center, the US Bank building was
constructed, um that was
a capture of
revenue tax revenue to help fund
improvements for this complex over here
as well. We found the initial plan and
project. However, we can't really find
any of the documentation that shows how
it all happened. We found the plan and
project.
So it's been done before.
>> I've got a follow-up question
maybe
on still on data centers.
One of the things there's a lot about
data centers I don't know.
Well, one of the things I've heard
recently are kind of like the buffers
between the data centers and the
residents.
Um for noise and all all sorts of other
things.
And
that might be
uh
public benefit use
for for those TIFs. I don't know.
>> Sure, that's good. We're hearing a lot
about the data centers right now. Um
it's is definitely a evolving dynamic
that is not a dynamic that's changing
here in Cheyenne, Wyoming only. It's
happening nationally.
I've been
talking to other uh planners including
the planning development director in
Weld County and the planning director
here. Um and we've talked about how
we're all seeing similar issues with man
camps, with data centers, uh with those
items. So, we're trying to figure out um
the best way to
collectively have the same conversations
with the same individuals to make sure
everyone's on board. But, then we do
have this um
a lot of
vocal um activism that's been showing up
at our meetings of the governing body.
And I think what used to be a pretty
quick and easy process, I think those
days have set sail.
Um it has come to our attention and a
lot of the data center uh folks have
been noting this that
this is all part of that AI race across
the globe between us, other countries,
and stuff like that. And there have been
discussions saying that a lot of this um
narrative has been planted by other
countries, other organizations to either
spread misinformation, to start a story,
and all of it's done through social
media.
And it's continuing to um affect people
and their opinions and thoughts.
You know, we talk about closed-loop
systems where really a single data
center is using the same amount of water
on a closed-loop system between like
five and 10 single-family houses
annually.
Uh we uh talk about um
other
um different elements like they are uh
just using tons of of energy and they're
going to pass those costs on to the
residents. That's that's not the case
here in Wyoming. We're one of the first
uh states uh to work to work with a
local utility um Black Hills Energy to
essentially create a tolling process
where large energy uh users are required
to offset every single cost um that's
associated with them
getting that energy. That's building the
power plant, that's distributing the
power, so that doesn't fall onto the
property owners. So, there's a lot of
things that we've been doing um that are
good models for the rest of the country.
Um now, the electrical tolling that I
just mentioned there
um from us being one of the first um in
the country to do that is my
understanding that most every state now
has a similar program. They've been
working to do that. Not all of them do,
but most everyone has. So, the
the discussion you see no matter no
matter how many times you try to get the
correct story out the incorrect
narrative continues to seem to to take
precedence.
Um
I I do know that Cheyenne Leads is
looking to
uh have an informational open house to
talk more about data centers. That's
that's on the horizon. I don't know when
their data is. We are in the early
stages of putting together a work
session for a governing body to
hopefully um identify what happens in
the data center process from
coordinating with the energy company to
coordinate with the Board of Public
Utilities um and then addressing some of
the overall myths and concerns that we
have.
Um so, those are all items that are on
our our plate. We're trying to continue
to work on that.
But, it's a it's a tough crowd right
now.
Um while we're sort of on the TIF topic
of eligibility and what you can use it
for
back in 2022, we took our first stab at
creating review criteria for uh tax
increment financing.
I would like um us to
start to dive into this a little bit
deeper
um if if you all wish in at one of our
upcoming meetings
number one, review of these are
accurate.
I really don't want to change them too
much because they're also embedded in
the bylaws but also look at if there's
ways we can expand it but also provide a
little bit more clarification for staff
uh for the governing body and also for
prospective developers as to um
identifying what is clearly eligible for
tax increment financing reimbursement.
Um for example, we've uh
generally said if it's a public
infrastructure improvement it's going to
be
eligible. So, that'd be curb, gutter,
sidewalk. We've also expanded to say if
you're doing uh you're creating a
building, a new building
uh with a facade that meets or exceeds
the development standards in that zone
district, like what Stencil had done,
what MHP had done uh those types of
projects we will um cover those because
you're going above and beyond and that's
a public benefit because you're
improving the the right of way. However,
um things that we
um
have been a little bit unclear on are,
well, how do we deal with the uh
renovation of existing buildings when
what we're doing is preventing one from
falling down, preserving it, uh
increasing public safety. You know, we
haven't been clear on is fire
suppression something that is
is eligible.
We treat it as eligible but it's not
clearly identified in our policy
documents. Is HVAC something that's
eligible?
If you have a system with a H a building
with an HVAC system that doesn't work
we are um looking at treating that as an
eligible expense because our building
code requires that when you rehab a
building. So, I think it'll be important
for us in the upcoming months to nail
down what's eligible, so people um know.
>> Chair, so you that brings up a question
for me. Um if something becomes
eligible, so for example, if a
if a developer comes in
and starts a project, it's already
planned, it's already funded, it's
already financed, it's already
purchased.
What is the time frame if something
becomes eligible that they can come back
and reapply?
>> Chair, um members of the board and
Commissioner Whitehead, so this would be
um if
someone were to do
improvements under a
authorized urban renewal plan and
project and they kind of change the
scope of what they wanted to to use it
for. We'll use the Bell Building, for
example. I think that's going to be a
great example. Um you all saw the Bell
Building relatively recently for a plan
and project. And since that plan and
project was put together, it is
completely shifted. Um they ran into
obstacles with the uh DOT when it came
to up to access, and they are pivoting
to uh a change.
Um with that one, we've been working
with the developer and the property
owner. Um they are intending to get
their plan finalized. They will come
back and revise their plan and project.
That is their intent to revise, unless
they can squeeze it into what's already
been
been described in that plan and project,
which was relatively broad.
Um so, we hope we can do that, but we'll
we'll bring that back to you all and
then back to the governing body.
>> So, even if they let's put in that
example, they changed, but what if it's
something that's already been funded? I
guess if a if the developer's already
completed the project and and then
is there a time frame to miss the
>> I'm chair members of the board, there
isn't a time frame for that. I'd have to
work with our city attorney to see how
that would
would work. Um basically what you're
saying is let's say a developer, let's
use Stencil for example, they wanted
land acquisition to account as an
eligible expense and it was denied.
Um
by the governing body. They pulled it
out of the development agreement. So
land was not included. Um say all of a
sudden everyone determines that land is
an eligible expense. Your question would
be could they come back and then request
reimbursement?
Uh the process there is is unwritten,
number one. It's not written. Um but
since the
development agreement details what is
authorized, they at minimum would have
to go back to the governing body to
request that the eligible expenses be
modified to include that new piece.
>> And I think part of the hardship, too,
at least when I think about it that way
under like that circumstances, if they
tried to come back later, the baseline
for the increment would be much higher.
At that point they've already done the
development, so I don't know that
there'd even be
>> That's true.
>> anything to recover.
>> Interim and board, it necessarily
wouldn't change the base or the baseline
or the beginning because of the
development agreement is the final piece
of the puzzle that just identifies after
the the base has been set, it identifies
what is eligible,
um
who the parties are that are getting the
the pledge for the payment.
So I I don't think it would have any
effect on
it would have no effect on the base. I
think it'd be as simple as just amending
out the development agreement, the
attachments to show that's eligible, and
then adding that into the
reimbursement
um equation. Now, the thing is is
those development agreements are
typically uh capped. Say you're able to
request up to $1 million. Um so, if this
new um
request is meant to help get them to
that maximum amount.
Um I can see it being easy if it's to
ask for
additional funding.
That could be problematic because that
would almost uh require a new pro forma
and a new uh gap analysis review to see
if that additional um
funding would change those um
those estimates and assumptions.
>> Okay. Any other other business,
comments, questions?
>> So, chair, members of the board, I'll uh
I'll I'll be getting some stuff out in
the next couple of months, I hope. I
probably will.
To be able to start to um look at what
we would
uh think is a good path forward on it.
Um the final thing I have to note is uh
after this budget year, we are looking
at um hiring a couple of different
positions in the planning and
development department. Um one of them
hopefully will be on board um at the
beginning of June. It's just an
internship, um but that will replace a
planner one. It's an intern that will
work here seasonally to help with
outreach. Um and then we're uh intending
to take remaining
uh
salary
uh allocations to hopefully hire a
deputy director in the planning and
development department. And the goal of
that deputy director is to be the one
who will spearhead the urban renewal
authority, as well as historic
preservation, to hopefully pull a couple
things off my plate cuz gosh darn it, I
need it.
No, I'm not leaving us.
I joke around [snorts] that I'm saying
that this making me more replaceable um
but I do I have nine different hats that
I wear on a daily basis in the planning
development department. So, I'm trying
to find ways to
um give other boards and commissions the
attention that they deserve cuz this
this one needs a a lot of attention cuz
it has a lot of good possibilities.
That's all I have for updates.
>> Okay. Anyone else? Any other business?
Yeah.
I will make a motion to adjourn.
>> Second.
>> All those in favor?
>> Aye.
>> Meeting is adjourned.
>> All right. Thank you.